GEORGIOS E. MAGDIS

Associate Professor - Villum Young Investigator Cosmic DAWN Center - Niels Bohr Institute - University of Copenhagen

Born: 24 June 1980 Nationality: Greek email: georgios.magdis@nbi.ku.dk Tel: +45-53775257

web: http://www.georgiosmagdis.com/ ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4872-2294

Address: Cosmic DAWN Centre, Juliane Maries Vej 30, 2100 Copenhagen O

RESEARCH INTEREST

My research lies in the area of observational cosmology and galaxy evolution. I focus on the study of the physical properties (e.g. stellar mass, star-formation rate, ISM) of distant galaxy populations aiming to shed light on the birth, formation, mass build-up, and evolution of galaxies throughout cosmic time. For my research, I use multi-wavelength data (ranging from X-rays to radio) and I specialise in infrared/submm/radio space as well as ground-based observations. I am leading and actively participate in numerous projects that aim to pioneered our view of galaxy evolution, develop new methods and tools to detect distant galaxy populations and study their physical properties in order to understand the origins and the history of our Cosmos.

EDUCATION

University of Oxford, UK

October 2008

DPhil in Astrophysics

Thesis title: Mid-Infrared Studies of Lyman Break Galaxies with the Spitzer Space Telescope

University of Crete, GR September 2005

 $MSc\ in\ Astrophysics$

University of Crete, GR September 2003

BSc in Physics

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Cosmic Dawn Center, NBI, DK

2018 -

Co-founder, Associate Professor

Dark Cosmology Center, NBI, DK

November 2015 - April 2018

Assistant Professor - DARK/Carlsberg Fellow

Young Investigator Program, Villum Foundation

January 2016 - present

Group Leader

National Observatory of Athens, GR

January 2014 - present

Adjunct Researcher

University of Oxford, UK

April 2011 - November 2015

Post-doctoral Research Fellow

Service d'Astrophysique, CEA, Saclay, FR
November 2008 - April 2011

Post-doctoral Fellow

FELLOWSHIPS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

DARK/Carlsberg Independent Research Fellowship, DARK Cosmology Center 2015 - 2018 School of Advanced Physics graduate Scholarship, University of Crete 2003 - 2005 Centers of Excellence, DNRF €8.5million (core member, co-founder)

Cosmic Dawn Center of Excellence

Young Investigator Program, Villum Foundation, €700k (PI)

Gas to stars - Stars to Dust; Exploring the star formation activity through Cosmic time

THALES Programme, €521k (co-I)

The invisible side of formation and evolution of supermassive Black Holes in the Universe

Astrophysical Data Analysis Program, NASA, \$116k (co-I)

Extreme silicate absorbers in WISE

PUBLICATIONS

I have published 120 articles in peer reviewed journals, 13 as a first author, that have received more than 8000 citations and I have an h-index of 52 (source NASA ADS). For a full list of my publication record see separate attachment.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

NBI, KU, DK 2018

Lecturer for the course: "Gravitational Dynamics and Galaxy Formation" - Block 3

University of Athens, GR 2016 and 2017

Invited lecturer on Galaxy Evolution Astronomy Summer School

University of Oxford, UK 2006 -2008 and 2011 - 2015

Demonstrator for the 3rd undergraduate course "Astrophysics Lab"

University of Crete, GR

Teaching Assistant, Demonstrator and Mark Evaluator for the courses "Classical Mechanics" and "Applied Mathematics"

2003-2005

SUPERVISION

Master Students	
E. Paspaliaris, University of Copenhagen (Principal)	2017 - present
Cecilie Sand Norholm, University of Copenhagen (Principal)	2017 - $present$
Marina Papathanasiou, DTU (Principal)	2017 - $present$
I. Cortzen, University of Copenhagen (Principal)	2015 - 2016
PhD Students	
I. Cortzen, University of Copenhagen (Principal)	2017 - $present$
C. Gomez Guijarro, University of Copenhagen (co)	2017 - $present$
J. Virdee, University of Oxford (co)	2012-2015
A. Tiley, University of Oxford (co)	2013-2015
Post-Docs	
F. Vallentino, University of Copenhagen (Principle)	2017-2020
L. Ciesla, University of Crete (co)	2013-2015

INTERNATIONAL RECOGNITION AND AWARDS

Enhanced Eurotalents, Proposal Reviewer	2017
NASA Astrophysical Data Analysis Program, Selection Committee	2017
ESO, Time Allocation Committee	2017-2018
ERC Starting Grant, Proposal Referee	2016
Royal Astronomical Society Group Achievement Award	2014
MNRAS, ApJ, A&A journals, Referee	2010 - $present$
32 Invited/Contributed Talks / 19 Colloquia	2010 - $present$

PRESS RELEASES AND OUTREACH

Maxwell Lecture Series, King's College, UK	2017
Talk: The History of the Universe; A story narrated by photons	
Master Intro cabin trip, Niels Bohr Institute	2017
Talk: The Cool Cosmos	
Work experience placement in astrophysics at the University of Oxford 2011 - 2	2015
A week of astronomer's daily work followed by school students	
	2014
Oxford University Science Blog	2014
Galactic star baby boom ended five billion years ago.	
Press release by the Royal Astronomical Societ	2012
GOODS-Herschel reveals gas mass role in creating fireworks versus beacons of star formation	
Astronomy & Astrophysics Highlights	2011
Herschel Reveals a new population of star forming Galaxies	
Press release by the European Space Agency	2011
Herschel paints a new story of galaxy evolution	
SELECTED TELESCOPE TIME ALLOCATION AND OBSERVING EXPERIENCE	
\mathbf{ALMA} (selected)	
	2018
Excitation conditions of the diffuse gas traced by [CI] in MS galaxies at $z \sim 1.2$, 11.5hrs (co-PI)	2018
Exploring the link between [CI] and PAHs in star-forming galaxies, 72.5hrs (ACA, co-PI)	
Obscuration to Reionization: A Blank-Field 2mm Deep Survey in COSMOS, 40,5hrs (co-I)	
What is the Origin and Subsequent Evolution of Starbursts at $z \sim 2$?, 19.4hrs (co-I)	
SFR and dust sizes, morphologies and dynamical masses of 42 galaxies at $z \sim 1.5$, 15.9hrs(co-I)	
Probing the Gas Reservoirs of Lensed Quiescent Galaxies at $z=1.6-3.2$ 10.6hrs(co-I)	
Towards a census of star-formation since $z \sim 6$ with ALMA-1.1mm, 21.2hrs, (co-I)	2017
Quiescence of quiescent galaxies at $z \sim 2$, 12.3hrs, (co-I)	2017
Direct detection of cold dust in $z \sim 1.6$ passive early-type galaxies, 11.4hrs, (co-I)	2017
A [CI] survey of high-redshift main-sequence galaxies, 8hrs, (co-I)	2016
What is the origin and subsequent evolution of starbursts at $z > 2$, 14.6hrs, (co-I)	2016
How do we get to the peak of the Cosmic Star Formation Rate Density, 1.2hrs, (co-I)	2016
Tracing the star formation law in the early Universe, 1.0hrs, (PI)	2016
ISM physics at high-z: cold gas and CO excitation for 75 galaxies at $z \sim 1.5$, 9.0hrs, (co-I)	2016
	2015
	2015
	2013
IRAM 30m and PdBI (selected)	
,	2018
	2017
Scaling Laws of star formation across cosmic time, 80hrs, (PI) 2015 - 2	
	2014
	2014 2014
	2014 2011
ESO - APEX (selected)	
	2013
Herschel Space Observatory (selected)	
_ ,	2012

Unravelling the physical processes that regulate star formation and AGN activity in ordinary galaxies at z = 2, 196.3hrs, (co-I)

Herschel Spectroscopic Survey of far-IR Infrared Fine Structure Lines in the Intermediate Redshift ULIRGs, 89hrs, (co-I)

2012

ESO-VLT (selected)

Can we use giant Ly α nebulae to trace the early heating of intracluster plasma in cluster progenitors?, 1night, (co-I)

A Kinematic Study of Herschel selected ULIRGs at z > 2, 1night (co-PI)

2016

The KMOS Kinematic Survey of ~ 1000 star-forming galaxies; Tracing their Dynamics, Star-Formation and Chemical Properties, 40 nights, (co-I)

A detailed Kinematic Study of star forming galaxies at z > 2, 1night, (co-PI)

2013

Observing experience: IRAM 30m * VLT (KMOS) * Palomar Observatory (SWIFT) * Caltech Sub-millimeter 10.4m Observatory * MMT (Hectospec) * Skinakas 1.3m Optical Observatory

MAIN COLLABORATIONS AND TEAMS

Major Collaborations

Cosmic Dawn Center, Dark Cosmology Center /NBI/KU (Denmark) * University of Oxford (UK) * CEA/Sacley (Paris, France) * Max Plank Institute for Extra-terrestrial Physics (MPE, Germany) * Center for Astrophysics (CfA/Harvard, USA) * National Optical Astronomy Observatory (NOAO, USA) * Caltech (USA) * University of Crete (Greece) * ESO (Germany) * IAASARS (National Observatory of Athens, Greece)

Major Teams

PEP * GOODS * GOODS-Herschel * HerMES * CLS * KROSS * COSMOS-Herschel * Candels-Herschel, * SPICA science consortium * FIRSPEX * HARMONI

TECHNICAL AND OTHER QUALIFICATIONS

Computers & Programming

Windows/Unix/MacOs; Fortran 77, Python, IDL, LATEX, HTML

Astronomical Packages

Starfinder, DAOPHOT, Sextractor, IRAF, GALFIT, PEGASE, Hyper-z, EASY, LePHARE, CIGALLE, SPICE (among others)

Languages

Native Greek, Fluent English, Conversational French

REFERENCES

Prof. Sune Toft, University of Copenhagen (sune@dark-cosmology.dk)

Dr David Elbaz, CEA/Saclay (elbaz@cea.fr)

Dr Emanuele Daddi, CEA/Saclay (edaddi@cea.fr)

Prof. Dimitra Rigopoulou, University of Oxford (dar@astro.ox.ac.uk)

Dr Jiasheng Huang, CfA/Harvard (jhuang@cfa.harvard.edu)

Prof. Martin Bureau, University of Oxford, (bureau@astro.ox.ac.uk)

Dr Mark Dickinson, NOAO (med@noao.edu)

Prof. Vassilis Charmandaris, University of Crete / NOA (vassilis@physics.uoc.gr)